To better understand some aspects of MCP,
we are going to start to implement
our own CLI-based chatbot.
This is going to give us a better idea
of how clients and servers actually work together.
In this video, I want to do a little bit of project setup
and just help you understand exactly
what we're going to make.
I've got a lot of product description over here
of what we're going to build.
We're going to go through all this over time.
For right now, I just want you
to get a high level understanding.
So as I mentioned, it's going to be a CLI-based chatbot.
We're going to allow users to work
with a collection of documents.
These are going to be fake documents.
They're just going to be stored in memory.
We're going to build out a small MCP client
that is going to connect to our own custom MCP server.
For right now, this server is going to have two tools
implemented inside of it.
One tool to read the contents of a document
and one tool to update the contents of a document.
Again, these documents over here on the right-hand side,
they're all fake.
So they are going to be persisted only in memory.
That's it.
Now, before we go any further,
there is a very important note.
Something I really want you to understand
around this entire process.
And that is that on a normal project,
typically we would be implementing either a client
or an MCP server.
So on a real project,
we might be authoring just an MCP server
to distribute to the world
and allow developers to access some service
that we have built up.
Alternatively, we might be building a project
where we make only a MCP client.
And the intent here would be that we would be connecting
to some outside MCP servers
that have already been implemented by some other engineers.
So in this project,
we are making both a client and a server.
And we're just doing that in one project
so you get a better understanding
of how this stuff actually works together.
All right, now that we have this disclaimer out of the way,
let's go through just a little bit of setup.
Attached to this video,
you should find a file named cliproject.zip.
Inside there is some starter code for our project.
Make sure you download that zip file,
extract it,
and then open up your code editor
inside of that project directory.
Just to save a little bit of time,
I have already done so.
So I've already got my code editor open
inside of that small project.
Inside this project,
I would encourage you to take a look
at the readme.md file.
Inside here, I've placed some setup directions.
So it's gonna walk you through the process
of making sure you put your API key
into the .env file inside this project.
And it's also gonna walk you through the process
of installing dependencies,
either with UV or without UV.
Once you have gone through all this setup,
you can then run the starter project right away.
To do so, inside of your terminal,
make sure that you are inside of your project directory.
So I called my project mcp.
And inside there,
I've got all my different project files and folders.
To run the project,
we will run uv run main.py
if you're making use of UV.
If you are not making use of UV,
then it will be just python main.py.
Now I'm making use of UV.
So I'm gonna do a uv run main.py.
And then when I run that,
I should see a chat prompt appear.
And if I ask what's one plus one,
I should see a response rather quickly.
That is it for our setup.
So now we can start to focus
on adding in some new features to this application.